In 1784, William Hollins starts a business in Pleasley, Derbyshire.
The business creates a fabric called Viyella.
Viyella is a signature Irish fabric loved by people around the world.
Viyella is registered as a trademark in 1894,
and in 1907, the trademark is registered in the US of A.
Woohoo!
But in the sixties,
many poor young girls who are kept in places called Magdalene asylums are made to work for Viyella.
Magdalene asylums were places where girls could be put
when they had a baby and the baby's father ran away.
Some of the girls got pregnant because they were raped.
Then they were put in a Magdalene asylum,
so the church could put their life back in order.
While they were staying in the Magdalene asylums,
the girls had a lot of work to do.
They were washing clothes in the laundries,
and they were making Viyella fabric too.
The church got money for the Viyella fabric,
but the church did not pay the girls any money for making the fabric.
Both the church and the Viyella business made good money.
The poor little penitents kept working and working,
and many of them stayed in the asylums for a long, long time.
In 2010, the Irish Human Rights Commission told the government that the penitents,
who are now old,
should finally get some money
for all the work that they did when they were young girls.
But the government did not do anything.
Anyhoo.
In 2024, Morrison McConnell celebrate 240 years of Viyella.
Viyella is a Morrison McConnell brand,
and Morrison McConnell will continue to give people
the Viyella fabric that they love.